<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An examination of the observations upon His Majesties answers. Wherein the absurdities of the observators positions, and inferences are discovered.</title>
            <author>Jones, John, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87638</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J968</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E65_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23238</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871941</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871941</idno>
            <idno type="VID">124359</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87638)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 124359)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 11:E65[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An examination of the observations upon His Majesties answers. Wherein the absurdities of the observators positions, and inferences are discovered.</title>
                  <author>Jones, John, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s. n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare of our Lord. M.DC.XLIII. [1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Jones. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy reads: "Aug:14 Oxon. 1643".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Parker, Henry, 1604-1652. --  Observations upon some of His Majesties late answers and expresses.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:124359:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXAMINATION OF THE OBSERVATIONS <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon His MAJESTIES ANSWERS.</p>
            <p>Wherein the abſurdities of the OBSERVATORS Poſitions, and Inferences are diſcovered.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Nunquámne reponam</l>
               <l>Vexatus toties rauci Theſeide Codri?</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Juvenal. Sat. 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare of our LORD. <hi>M.DC.XLIII.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:124359:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:124359:2"/>
            <head>AN EXAMINATION OF THE OBSERVATIONS <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon his MAJESTIES ANSWERS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E ſhall for methods ſake, firſt take a generall examination of the Obſervators chiefeſt Poſitions, and their ſuppoſed properties: then fall to a ſtricter examination of them, upon a particular ſurvey of the whole diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe: not omitting the leaſt argument materially urged by him; which we pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to diſcuſſe in that order, the nature of the thing exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and examination doth prompt us to; not limiting our ſelfe to any particular government, but looking upon all in their efficients and ends: deſcending to particulars only and as often as the Obſervator goeth before us: The principall ſubject of his diſcourſe is, <hi>That power is originally inherent in the people,</hi> pag. 1. <hi>and transferred by them alwayes upon certaine limitations and conditions of reentry,</hi> pag. 4, 5. he taketh this admitted and then urgeth the following properties incident to the people.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:124359:3"/>
            <q>
               <hi>The people more noble than the King,</hi> pag. 3.</q>
            <p>He proveth this by two reaſons.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. From the end. <hi>The King is for the people inſtituted, not the people for the King.</hi> pag. 3.</item>
               <item>2. From the cauſe. <hi>Quod facit tale eſt magis tale,</hi> pag. 2.
<p>
                     <hi>The King is</hi> ſingulis major, univerſis minor, pag. 2, 44.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What Parliaments be, and the prayſes of them,</hi> pag. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.</p>
                  <p>Hothams <hi>reſiſting the Kings entrance into Hull is juſtifyed,</hi> pag 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31.</p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe opinions are maintained, ſaving that of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and <hi>Hothams</hi> act by Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> with all the reaſons uſed by the Obſervator. <hi>L</hi> 1. <hi>de pont. c.</hi> 7. <hi>et de Clericis. c</hi> 28. and Theologically anſwered by our late Brittiſh <hi>Solomon</hi> of happy memory; the firſt that I obſerved of Engliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants that ſeemeth to favour this opinion, is the Gentleman who delivered upon the Earle of <hi>Straffords</hi> tryal theſe words, <hi>If a King by the right of a Conquerour gives laws to the people, ſhall not the people by the ſame reaſon be reſtored to the right of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, to recover their liberty if they can:</hi> if indifinitely meant for all people; if by conquered is meant the people, it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to me that he ſuppoſeth the originall of all governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to proceed from the people.</p>
            <p>The Obſervators arguments pretend to be drawne from the fundamentals of nature, which ſhall be diſcuſſed in their proper places, a Chriſtian Writer in a buſineſſe of this weight, ſhould haue had his recourſe to Scripture, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured nature by it, which is the true Lydian ſtone, to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh ſpurious from genuine principles of nature, the ſacred booke is copious and evident in this matter, but becauſe not urged by the Obſervator, I ſhall content my ſelfe to paſſe by the great advantage Scripture giveth me, and touch it only with that caution I limited my ſelfe in the enſuing Treatiſe.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Power you ſay is originally inherent in the people.</hi>
            </q>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:124359:3"/>
            <p>You ſay ſo, but offer no proofe of it.</p>
            <p>What power? to make Kings? all Kings? or ſome Kings? at all times? or ſome times? and is this power originally inherent in them <hi>de facto</hi> or <hi>de jure,</hi> if <hi>de jure</hi> is it <hi>divino, naturali,</hi> or <hi>jure Gentium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>De facto,</hi> Ignorance it ſelfe hath not the face to averre it, dominion is the chiefe ingredient of Royalty: <hi>Adam</hi> had it, and uſed it over man and beaſt, a gift not of man but of God, <hi>Geneſ. c.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 28. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> after his likeneſſe, after his image God created man: his image in the ſubſtance, eſpecially ſoule of man, his likeneſſe in the qualities he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed man with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> like God, as he was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtrong powerfull: ſtrength and power being eſſentiall properties of ſoveraignty, the poſterity of the firſt man before the law, when they were a law to themſelves, had <hi>poteſtatem vitae et necis</hi> derived to their firſt borne in their generations, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly booke averreth this: no moderne, no antient authority oppugneth it. <hi>Poteſtas vitae et necis,</hi> are infallible markes of Soveraignty, conſtantly exerciſed by the firſt borne before the Law, without limitation without condition or contract had with them over whom they exerciſed this authority, how then is <hi>Power originally inherent in the people,</hi> did the conſtant practiſe of the firſt age runne a courſe contrary to nature in morall buſineſſes for the ſpace of ſixteen hundred years: for from the creation to the deluge about ſo many yeares are reckoned by the beſt Chronologers: neither is this birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right of ſoveraignty during that time ſuſpended, interrupted, or croſt in the lyne of <hi>Seth,</hi> for ought I ever heard or read of: no man I believe is of that unbeliefe, to ſay, that nature from its cradle was diſpoſſeſſed of this birth-right, and could not regaine it in ſo many ages, it is ſaid <hi>Naturam expellas furcâ li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> recurret,</hi> leſſe time than this might make cuſtome na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, unleſſe this cuſtome did croſſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>prima na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae,</hi> which we ſhall examine in its proper place: the purity
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:124359:4"/>of nature probably in morall actions, grew more corrupted in proceſſe of ages; witneſſeth the increaſe of lawes, occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by the encreaſe of vice: After the Deluge, <hi>Nimrod</hi> put up the firſt Monarchy; the People had not the chiefe hand to elect him; but you reply, he was a Hunter of men, a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, an Inverter of Natures Inſtitutions. what Nature meant, or aſſented to, ſhall be examined in one conſideration of Inherent power, <hi>De jute naturali:</hi> that he was a Monarch and not elected by the People, fully ſatisfieth our preſent purpoſe: he is branded with Tyranny, not ſo properly for uſurpation of Soveraignty, but for the unnaturall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate exerciſe of his Dominion; for he in whom Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty is lawfully veſted, be it from People, or Patrimoniall and inheritable from his Anceſtours, by the unnaturall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of his power is ordinarily and properly ſtiled a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant: the World being Peopled, ſeverall Dominions aroſe of ſeverall natures, one man ſometimes, and in ſome places ingroſſing Soveraignty, and ſome times the people: the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of depraved Nature ſtill breaking our for their ſeeming beſt advantage: to run upon particulars is needleſſe, nor much to the purpoſe, examples of both natures are nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; though queſtionleſſe unequall: the foure Monarchs, and the practice of the firſt age owne not their births to popular elections: examples parallell to theſe for antiquity, and fame the continued voyce of Hiſtory aſſureth me can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be found in any election made by the people: hence it is evident, that it cannot without much Immodeſty or Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance be alleadged, that Power is originally inherent in the People, <hi>de facto,</hi> in reſpect of practice in the People, to make all Kings, and at all times.</p>
            <p>Whether this power is originally inherent in the People <hi>de jure</hi> of right, falleth next to be examined: if this power is originally inherent in the people <hi>de jure,</hi> it is then ſo inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in them <hi>jure Divino,</hi> by Divine right, naturally by the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:124359:4"/>law of Nature, or <hi>jure Gentium,</hi> by the law of Nations; to averre the people intituled to this power by any Civill law; that is, by the law of any particular Nation, commeth not to the purpoſe: for your tenent is indefinite, not limited to any particular government; and endeavoured to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by indefinite arguments: therefore if the people hath any right to this power we muſt finde it out in one of the three rights propoſed by us, and we will here firſt enquire after this power in the Divine law.</p>
            <p>God is donour of all Dominions witneſſeth your ſelfe, <hi>page</hi> 1. therefore not the people. but you will ſay God and the people: to prove this, I finde not one argument drawne from Scripture in all your Obſervations, and if any text had the leaſt colour of advantage for you, without doubt it had beene urged: and ſacred Hiſtory is moſt energeticall and too frequent in the mouth of conſcious Heterodoxy, we ſhall to keepe cloſer to you, decline to examine your Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons according to the rule of Scripture, and keep our diſcourſe to runne within the Channels of naturall Reaſon; touching only Divinity as we paſſe along, ſo far as it deſcendeth to communicate it ſelfe with reaſon: if you muſt needs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore juſtle in man to ſhare with God in the conſtitution of Royalneſſe, reaſon (reaſon and nature being the Idols of your diſcourſe) forceth you to confeſſe, that God is either the mediate, people immediate; or the people mediate, God the immediate, or both immediately concurre as immediate efficients of principalities: no other ſort of operation or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flux can be aſſigned to efficient Cauſes, and reducible to the Obſervations advantage: if God is made to be mediate, peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple immediate efficients, it followeth of neceſſity, that the people muſt either be a meer inſtrument, or a free Agent ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by the firſt cauſe, to ſettle this power in whom they pleaſe; and that in an abſolute or conditionall eſtate: a meere inſtrumentall Cauſe, I am aſſured you will deny the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:124359:5"/>people to bee, for <hi>Inſtrumentum non movet niſi motum:</hi> and the effects of it, are properly and uſually called the effect of the mover, I meane by mover, not the finall cauſe, but effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent or Agent, which indeed hath the moſt influence upon the effect, and whoſe quality ſtill ſpecificates and denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates accordingly this efficient, and not the inſtrument: he that killeth a man with a Sword, is called the man-ſlayer, not the Sword: a virtuous or vicious exploit is attributed to the man, not the ſword wherewith he did it: to take God and people in this ſtate, is to allow God to be the Well from whence doth flow principality, and the people the Conduit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipe: and he that hath the leaſt drop of Reaſon, will not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verre the water to have its being from the Conduit-pipe, that conveyeth it: people in this notion have not the powers dreamed of by the Obſervations, either originall or inherent in them; nor can your <hi>quod fecit tale, eſt magis tale</hi> be applyed to them, that have not ſufficiency fit to denominate them <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le;</hi> we ſhall looke then upon the people as free Agents, ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by God, the mediate or remoter Cauſe, with power by them grantable and transferrable upon whomſoever their publike voyce and conſent electeth; this power is by them grantable abſolutely, or conditionally; or both, if they may doe it both wayes; wee will for methods ſake looke upon them in their firſt capacity; if they make an abſolute grant, they are irrevocably concluded; neither is it of any purpoſe to urge, that the nature of the thing granted is incompatible with an abſolute conveyance of it, this is to deny our ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: neither doth the nature of the thing granted, gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay an abſoluteneſſe of grant; for power ever lives and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, is at moſt the thing conveyed; which was and may be abſolutely and irrevocably given; a free man by the law of this Land, may by confeſſing himſelfe a villaine in a Court of Record, bind himſelfe and his heires to ſervitude and eſtate to the diſpoſall of their Lord: a man <hi>ſui juris</hi> in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:124359:5"/>the Romane Law, uſually called the Civill law, may ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject himſelfe and poſterity to another man, over whom and fortunes he hath an abſolute Dominion, <hi>Gell. l.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 8. and <hi>Inſtinian. Inſtitut: de ſervis;</hi> the Jewiſh Law hath an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe teſtimony for this addition in 21. Chapter of <hi>Exodus, verſe</hi> 6. his Maſter, ſpeaking of Servant, he ſhall boare his eare through with an Awle; and he ſhall ſerve him for ever; the Logicke of theſe examples is evident; by the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that one, ſo many that are <hi>ſui iuris,</hi> may convey to one or more abſolute dominion over themſelves and poſterity. And though I would admit unto you, that it is, <hi>pag.</hi> 20. <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall for any Nation to give away its owne propriety in it ſelfe,</hi> and yet this gift is both naturall and neceſſary to the being of all Societies and States; for if every man reſerveth to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the power given him by nature to reſiſt violence and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury; though offered by a Magiſtrate; then every man would be a law to himſelfe, to the extirpation of all Societies and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Juſtice.</p>
            <p>The inconveniency ariſing from the ſuppoſition of ſuch ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute grant objected by the obſervator faleth to the ground, for conditionall as well as abſolute tralation of power is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to inconveniences, neither is it inſiſted ſo much by us, whether this power is ever or more uſually granted; but whether rightfully grantable irrevocably, which no reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble judgement will deny by the examples urged by us, drawn from the Conſtitutions of thoſe three moſt conſiderable Common-wealths, neither is this abſolute ſubjection, as the Obſervator falſly urgeth, contrary or diſſonant to the Law of Nature: by the Law of Nature hee underſtandeth that which right reaſon aſſenteth unto, <hi>pag.</hi> 44. Naturall reaſon many times approveth and conſenteth to this irrevocable conveyance: poverty ſometimes, or inability to defend themſelves by the ſtrength of their owne Lawes, compelleth the people irrevocably to ſubject themſelves to another po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:124359:6"/>and right reaſon aſſenteth to this grant, induced there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by theſe or the like exigences of State. <hi>Campani</hi> (ſaid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable <hi>Grotius</hi>) <hi>olim neceſsitate ſubacti, populo Romano ſe ſubiecerunt in hunc modum: populum Campanum vrbemque Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puam agros, delubra Deum, Divina Humanaque in veſtram ditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem P. C. dedimus;</hi> here is an abſolute conveyance over lives and fortunes by the people, without reſervations or condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: neither ſtandeth this example ſingle in Hiſtory: Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Grotius</hi> in his exquiſite book <hi>De Jure Belli &amp; pacis</hi> fol. 49. reckoneth many Conveyances of the ſame nature, which for brevitie we paſſe over, referring the ſcrupulous, if any can be in a matter ſo evident, to the foreſaid cited Author to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied, and ſhall further view the ſuperſtructure of your diſcourſe upon the foundation your ſelfe have laid: Admit Supremacie derived from the people, hence <hi>Quod facit tale eſt magis tale, The people more noble than the King, becauſe he is for them, not they for him instituted.</hi> Salus populi Suprema Lex, <hi>and the Law of prerogative is ſubſervient to this: the King,</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis major univerſis minor; <hi>the right of conqueſt cannot bee pleaded to acquit Princes of that which is due to the people, as the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors and ends of all power; for meere force cannot alter the courſe of Nature, or fruſtrate the tenour of Law, and if it could, there were more reaſon why the people might inſtiſie force to regaine due Liberty, then the King might ſubvert the ſame.</hi> And this is all I finde in your Obſervations reducible to maintaine the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall ſubject of your obſervation: the reſidue being either matter of fact, admonitions or reprehenſions, I ſhall not med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with, being Heterogencous to our preſent purpoſe, <hi>Quod facit tale &amp;c.</hi> Wine maketh a man drunk, therefore Wine it ſelfe is more drunke than man: the inference holdeth not you ſee in cauſes by accident. <hi>Sol &amp; homo generant hominem;</hi> therefore the Sunne is more man then the man generated; this I am aſſured you will confeſſe to bee a very bad conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; ſo then the Maxime is not current in partiall effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:124359:6"/>and the people are at moſt but partiall cauſes; for you allow God alſo a ſharer of this Supremacie: but I will admit further unto you; Supremacie wholly derived from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: the maxime is not true in all totall cauſes: <hi>Adam</hi> was the author or cauſe of ſinne; God was the totall Author or cauſe of <hi>Adam,</hi> therefore God was more Author or Cauſe of ſinne: your Religion will not allow this Logick; the ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iome therefore holdeth not in totall free agents, and though I admit you the people to be whole cauſe of this power, yet I know you will ſay they are free Agents in conferring of it; and if you allow them that freedome, your Axiome you ſee is ill applyed. To come yet nearer unto you, a Servant gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the Maſter the title of Maſter: Relatives as theſe are, are <hi>Cauſa ſibi invicem</hi> doth it follow therefore that the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant is more Maſter, then he that is made maſter by him: the paſſage betweene <hi>Valentinian</hi> and his Souldiers recorded by <hi>Sozom.</hi> in his Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory cleareth the point, <hi>Vt me ad imperandum vobis eligeretis, in veſtra ſitum erat potestate ô milites; at postquam me elegiſtis, quod petitis in meo est arbitrio, non veſtro; vobis tanquam ſubditis competit parere, mihi quae faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda ſunt cogitare:</hi> That <hi>I</hi> was choſen your Emperour lay in your power, Souldiers, but after I am ſo choſen by you, what you demand of me, lyeth now in mine, not your power, it befits you as ſubjects to obey, and me to conſider what <hi>I</hi> am to doe. Your <hi>Quod facit iale</hi> in point of government hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth true in him or them, whoſe power continually depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon the will of him or them that gave it, not in them who have it tranſacted by one Act, bee it abſolute or with certaine limitation, that this power is tranſactable is allowed by your ſelfe, and that abſolutely, ſome thing is alreadie proved; the conditionall relation of it we ſhall referre to be further examined, in the ſecond member of the diviſion of immediate efficients; and here we will ſift the ſecond pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie you annex to the ſubject of your diſcourſe, this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:124359:7"/>popular Supremacie. <hi>The People more noble than the King, becauſe he for them, not they for him is instituted:</hi> that univerſally taken, is apparently falſe: ſome Government is onely for the Governour, not the Governed erected; as that between the Maſter and Servant; whom the Maſter taketh for his own, not his Servants profit; and though the Servant gaineth by the ſervice, yet his gain was neither the cauſe nor end of this dominion; not of that gained by conqueſt, the end and efficient of ſome Government are both the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Governed; as that between the Husband and the Wife, whoſe ſubjection ſtill referreth to her and her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands goods. So the <hi>Campani</hi> ſubjected themſelves to <hi>Rome</hi> for their own ſafetie, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Honour and greatneſſe; both you ſee proved the object of this Government; the Conquerour is the efficient and end of his Government; by his contract with the people to limit his power with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain caution over them, maketh them thereby a partiall end of his Supremacie; it is falſe then that all Kings are erected for the people, and not the people for them; but that you may perceive the weakneſſe of your inference, I ſhall admit unto you, that all Kings are for the people, and not the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for them; doth it follow therefore, they are more noble than the King: tutorage is inſtituted for pupillage, not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillage for it; is the pupill therefore more noble than the tutour that hath power over him; the tutour upon miſuſage of his power over the pupill I confeſſe is removed; but by a poſitive Law made by thoſe above him; where that poſitive Law is, &amp; by whom made, appeareth not in any conſiderable Monarch of the world. ſome but ſew and inconſiderable Antiquitie make mention of <hi>Mezentius</hi> in <hi>Virgil</hi> ſeemed to be of ſuch conditionall powers.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ergo omnis furiis ſurrexit Etruria justis,</l>
               <l>Regem ad ſupp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>sium praſenti morte repoſcunt.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This pretended Nobi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itie we have quitted the people of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:124359:7"/>by what is already ſaid. Next your <hi>Salus populi, ſuprema lex,</hi> commeth to be diſcuſſed: if you mean by People a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth with all the parts of it, I allow you that <hi>Salus populi ſuprema lex,</hi> but if you underſtand by people the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject <hi>contrà</hi> diſtinguiſhed fom the King, if you take people for the Members without the Head of a Societie, your <hi>Salus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli</hi> is not <hi>Suprema lex:</hi> if you take Members apart, the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier Member challengeth the firſt reſpect, and conſequently the King, who is the Head of the Common-wealth, claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in reaſon the preheminence of the inferior Members: Art imitateth Nature; and if the Reaſon of Nature giveth it ſo, Reaſon of policie being grounded upon that of Nature can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny this prerogative: and ſo much concerning that adjunct. <hi>Rex ſingulis maior, univerſis minor:</hi> you underſtand <hi>maior &amp; minor</hi> in reſpect of Supremacie; and by <hi>univerſis, ſingulis ſimul ſumptis,</hi> all the Subjects, and the repreſentation of them the Parliaments, for they you ſay are eſſentially the ſame, <hi>pag.</hi> 5. He can command <hi>all ſingly, but all ioyntly can command him.</hi> This of all your opinions carrieth moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurditie with it. The people you ſay give a power over them to the King, and yet reſerve it to themſelves. In the Oath of Supremacie you confeſſe the King ſupreme next under God; but by this you introduce an interpoſition of the people; the repreſentative Bodie of the Kingdom the Parliament which is the Kingdom it ſelfe, ſo you terme it, <hi>pag.</hi> 5. do joyntly and univerſally in moſt acts preface the King, with May it pleaſe your moſt Excellent Majeſtie, if it proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from an inferiour to his ſuperiour, he cannot chooſe but take it as a jeare, or at leaſt a complement of ignorance: miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes and ignorance are incompatible with that infallibilitie you deifie the Parliament with; the King in reſpect of the <hi>univerſi,</hi> all the Subiects, muſt of neceſſitie be conſidered as Head of them, or a ſubordinate Member. If a Head, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie muſt be incident to it; the Head commandeth the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:124359:8"/>parts to obey; if a Member, He muſt obey them, to be cut off or left according to the Head, the <hi>univerſi'es</hi> Judgement: this is to meet more than halfe way with the Jeſuits; let not your popular Kinglineſſe ſtoop to a diſhonourable league with the children of <hi>Belial.</hi> I ſhall not more enlarge my ſelfe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute this abſurditie, though I conceive this enough to any unpreiudicated man. Another hath gone before me upon this ſubiect, who did very rationally diſcover the ſillineſſe, nay contradiction of this paradox. I ſhall paſſe over that of the holy Text, <hi>Statuam ſupra me Samuel,</hi> and urge ſome authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie drawn from Heathens, to ſhame this opinion from a Chriſtian Head; <hi>Marcus Aurelius, Magistratus de privatis principes de magistratibus, Deum de principibus judicare, Hor. Regum timendorum in ipſos greges, &amp; in ipſos reges imperium est Jovis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Hom. Il.</hi> 1. <hi>Otanes in Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to do what he will, and not bound to give an account to any, <hi>Dion Penſeenſis,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, So to governe that he is not accomptable to another, <hi>Dion lib.</hi> 5.3. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, He is free, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving power over himſelfe and Law, ſo what he pleaſeth he doth; what diſpleaſeth him he doth not; this indefinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of power few Kings at this day have; time and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon occaſionall reaſons of State bring Kings to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to limit their power to certain rules agreed upon by themſelves and people: and theſe rules have divers degrees of latitude, which the poſitive Lawes of many Countries do manifeſt and diſtinguiſh, but to whom the King is to yeild his accompt for breach of his Covenant, we ſhall touch hereafter; and here fall to diſcuſſe the laſt remarkable proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie your obſervation attributed to this ſuppoſed Ochlo-Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie. <hi>The right of Conquest cannot be pleaded to acquit Princes of that which is due to the People as the Authours and ends
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:124359:8"/>of all power, for meer force cannot alter the courſe of nature, or frustrate the tenor of Law, and if it could there were more reaſon why the People might justifie force to regain due libertie, than the Prince might to ſubvert the ſame.</hi> People are not the ſole end or Authours of this power, and if they were, the nature of the thing granted may be abſolutely transferred by them, without expreſſe or tacit condition, as is fully proved alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: then it followeth, the right of Conqueſt may be plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to acquit Princes of that which is due, you mean to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the people the end and Author of Government, to acknowledge them the Authours of it, with power to cancell the Authoritie given when they pleaſe, to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a ſupremacie in the Prince derived from the People, and nevertheleſſe ſtill to reſide in the People: how then doth meer force alter the courſe of nature or fruſtrate the tenor of Law, the Law of Nature you intend, if a Prince gaineth a Principalitie from him upon whom it was abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely conferred, ſuppoſe from People? the Conquerours Title ſtandeth firme againſt all, but the rightfull Owner: and the People if they have a Title or intereſt in this power, more than ſeldome conclude them for ever: the examples we have already urged queſtionleſſe force any impartiall Judgement to believe it. The moſt conſiderable Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies, (and the greateſt Govenments were Monarchies) the preſent or paſt age preſenteth to us were begun and ſetled by Conqueſts; and that theſe Monarches deſcended to cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with their Subjects to regulate their power by certain limitation deſired and approved by the People, hath more of the Princes bountie than obligation in it, being a free dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive beſtowed upon the people, and if the Covenant in part or in all is infringed or broken by the King, what advantage the people hath by it, paſſeth my underſtanding to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend; a Title of re-entry cannot be reſerved by them, from whom no eſtate paſſed; and if it did, this reſervation muſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:124359:9"/>be expreſſed or implied; we have no expreſſion of it urged by you, and we are aſſured you cannot produce any popular Charter with this expreſſe reſervation; and if this is impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, this impliedneſſe you muſt diſcover unto us either by reaſon or authoritie: this Supremacie is of that indifferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, that may be transferred conditionally or abſolutely: and I demand of you whether a tacit condition is ever an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed naturally, (I mean by the Law of Nature to take off the Conſtitutions of municipall Lawes therein) to a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe conveyable with ſuch indifferencie; to affirme it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth the nature of all abſolute grants. The Jewes claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves free from all Pagan Juriſdiction, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> was their King by that right the ſword did give him, if that right was not warrantable, the edicts grounded upon that right, might iuſtly be diſobeyed by the Jewes: Chriſt preached obedience to them, for he paid the generall taxati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on impoſed by <hi>Caeſar</hi> upon the Jewes and others in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man dition, exhorted thoſe to the ſame actuall obedience, who came with an intent to entrap him; where then is your frequent diſtinction? All lawfull Powers come from God, and are to be obeyed; unlawfull are not of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to be obeyed; this power is unlawfull I am aſſured you are ready to averre in moſt reſpects, in reſpect of title, and in reſpect of the thing enioyned, for a free Nation to pay a tribute, to part with their goods to a Pagan, to a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in Iſrael; yet though the thing commanded, though the title is by your own confeſſion unlawfull, it is enioyned not onely not to be reſiſted, but unfainedly obeyed by the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Law-giver, and the laſt Expoſitour of it our bleſſed Saviour. The Chriſtians of the firſt age ſealed this obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with their deareſt bloud, here then falleth your exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the <hi>Generaliſsimo, pag.</hi> 4. to be conſidered, his ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are exempted from his ſubiection, if he turneth the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons upon his own people; I grant it, his Commiſſion is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:124359:9"/>from the King, who giveth him power over his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, to deſtroy or puniſh them onely, and as often as they do tranſgreſſe poſitive edicts; but they are not his Souldiers or his Subiects in ſo large a manner as they are to their King; and if they were, the one is entituled to them by God, at leaſt partially, the other wholly by man. Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> a ſtrong Champion for the Engliſh Libertie in his Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>fol</hi> 1. ſayth, that the King holdeth the Lands hehath as King immediately from God, becauſe he hath, ſaith he, no ſuperiour but the Almightie. <hi>Bracton</hi> is of the ſame language, <hi>Omnis quidem ſub eo, ipſe ſub nullo niſi tantùm deo: Omnis</hi> not <hi>ſinguls,</hi> to take off your <hi>ſingùlis maior univerſis minor:</hi> and <hi>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùm ſub deo,</hi> ſpoken negatively, to exclude this eclipſe, this interpoſition of the people. But of this ſufficiently already is ſpoken. It cannot be objected to the Martyrs of the firſt age, that they could not reſiſt the torture they were at the leaſt ſeemingly willing to undergo. <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Apologie tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the Emperour, the Chriſtians were more in number, and ſtronger, and able to defend themſelves: his Scholar <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> is of the ſame Language, <hi>Quamvis nimins &amp; copioſus noſter populus, non tamen adverſus violentiam ſe ulciſcitur. Lactantius</hi> confirmeth him, <hi>lib.</hi> 5. and <hi>Auguſt.</hi> in many places of his <hi>De Civitate Dei.</hi> Of all other the paſſage between the <hi>Thebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Legion is moſt conſiderable, and the Emperour <hi>Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> they conſiſted of 6666 Souldiers, the Emperour ſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them upon pain of death to commit formall idolatrie; they refuſed to obey his command, they were able enough to reſiſt him and his power, they knew and confeſſed it, they laid their heads to the blocke, and lifted no hand againſt him: his command was injuſt, was impious; by natures dictates they were to conſerve themſelves; yet they relinquiſhed na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yielded to die. Let us compare <hi>Hothams action</hi> to this primitive paſſage, the King would have entred the gates of <hi>Hull,</hi> a Town within his Dominion, <hi>Hotham</hi> being within,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:124359:10"/>the Kings alleageance ſhut the gates againſt him, reſiſting his entrance with armed men; <hi>Hotham</hi> conceived his entrance would put his life in jeopardie, and the Kingdomes ſafetie endangered; he conceived it probably not inevitably to follow thereupon; ſuppoſe the ruine of both had inevitably enſued; yet it is not ſo farre preſt. The <hi>Thebean</hi> example doth not warrant the reſiſtance, they obeyed to the loſſe of life: this deſire to enter the Town came from the Cavaliers and ill Councellours, not from the King himſelfe. <hi>Caeſars</hi> taxation was by his miniſters aſſeſſed, collected, and proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly invented. <hi>Maximians</hi> ſervants brought the command to the <hi>Thebean</hi> Legion to commit idolatrie, they brought the puniſhment and executed it, and it was very probable they were the authours of both: yet no reſiſtance made againſt the Emperours command, though delivered by his miniſters; yet our King in perſon, and <hi>vivâ voce</hi> demanded entrance, and was reſiſted; and reſiſtance of the Kings authoritie is to reſiſt the King, as was declared by this preſent Parliament, upon the Earle of <hi>Strafford;</hi> triall: you will object, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour had a more abſolute Dominion, than our King hath, over his Subjects perſons and eſtates; I confeſſe it, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours power was in moſt things illimited; the Kings li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited by our municipall Lawes, obliged by a ſolemne Oath to keep them; and if he commandeth any thing oppoſite to theſe Lawes, we are not bound to obey this command; but we are not warranted by this Law to reſiſt the King with force of Armes, if other Chriſtians made a conſcience actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to reſiſt their Kings command even in things contrary to the Law of Nature and the divine Law, and thoſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned ſalvation, and can the conſcience of our Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie allow us to raiſe Armes to reſiſt the Kings commands, ſuppoſed by inferences to prove deſtructive to our poſitive Lawes? Our Law doth not warrant us, and if it did there is no warrant for that Law given by the ſupreme Law-giver.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:124359:10"/>But this reſiſtance is approved by Parliament; by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is meant by you the repreſentative Bodie of the Lords and Commons, aſſembled by the Kings Authoritie. I denie this to be Parliament by the Conſtitution of this Kingdom without the concurrence of the King, and if it were, I deny that the greater part is conſcious of this reſiſtance; and if the greater part were, I deny an infallibilitie tied to them; and if they were infallible, I deny that they alone without the King are competent Judges, makers and declarers of Law; if they were, then they ſhould be both parties and Judges, and diſpoſers of that which belongeth to the King, <hi>jure perſonae,</hi> without his conſent, himſelfe being neither there in perſon, nor repreſented by them or any of them; an opinion diſſonant to reaſon or conſcience, and the inſtitution of nature for the Members to raiſe Armes againſt the Head. <hi>Aeſop</hi> giveth us an example, and the effect of ſuch War; and hereupon we will digreſſe a little to examine the definition and properties given by your Obſervations to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which you define, <hi>pag.</hi> 5. to be the eſſence of the Kingdom, that's falſe, for a thing cannot be ſeparated from its eſſence; the Kingdom and Parliament can. A thing hath no being when the eſſence is deſtroyed; the Kingdom hath its being when the Parliament is ſuppreſſed, diſſolved, or not <hi>in rerum natura,</hi> as in the vacancie of a Parliament: the ſame numericall qualities that inhere in the Parliament do not inhere in the Kingdom, and ſo <hi>è eontra:</hi> the Parliament may be ſicke at the time the Kingdom is well, the Parliament may erre, when the Kingdom doth not: in the ſame manner, that generall Councels the repreſentative Bodie of the militant Church may erre when the Church generall doth not. This repreſentative Bodie is a ſelect number of men intruſted for a greater, with a large Commiſſion to treat and conclude for the truſters good: the truſters are men and ſubject to er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, unleſſe a ſupernaturall aſſiſtant ſpirit of infallibilitie is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:124359:11"/>neceſſarily pinned to their ſleeves: that they are remoter than ordinary Courts from erring I allow you, but not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely free from it, as you averre, <hi>pag.</hi> 8. The praiſes you give to Parliaments ſwell up moſt of your Obſervations: and much are I confeſſe deſervedly attributed. For mine own part, as I was borne under the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, ſo I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it without affectation the exquiſiteſt I know of: and in theſe the Parliament ſhineth above other Conſtitutions, <hi>ut inter ignes Luna minores.</hi> Let a Parliament run within its own channell, if it breake the bankes it overwhelmes, it deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth publique Libertie, and looſeth its being, and the end for which it was inſtituted. I love the fundamentall Libertie of this Kingdom, as well as the Obſervatour doth, but without dotage, as the Obſervator profeſſeth to love monarchicall Government, <hi>pag.</hi> 41. Parliaments have done wrong, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth the depoſall of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, therefore it is good Logicke to ſay they may do wrong. But you ſay, they were forced by <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth his victorious Armie, <hi>p.</hi> 32. I ſay ſo too, then they may be forced, and force we know are of ſeverall nature, I pray God the preſent be not conſcious of it; I leave to the effect ofevery Parliament to elogize it ſelfe. Parliaments are of a ſoveraigne good, but as in naturall ſo in politickes, I believe, <hi>Corruptio optimi est peſsima:</hi> and ſo much for Parliaments. We ſhall now reflect upon the next mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of our diviſion that falleth next in order to be diſcuſſed: that this Supremacie is grantable and granted by the people upon what condition and limitation beſt pleaſeth them, they are ſo enabled by expreſſe or tacit cauſalitie of the firſt cauſe mediate and remoter God: if tacitly, it is an inſtinct contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with them, and then it falleth properly to be diſcuſſed in the Law of Nature, which we ſhall conſider in its due place; if expreſly, either it is committed to writing, and ſo in the ſacred Book, or elſe traditionally practis'd by all ages and confeſſed by all or moſt Nations: neither of theſe is preſſed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:124359:11"/>or can be juſtly by you: hence we have clearly evinced, that the people by the divine Law cannot be the immediate effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of this Supremacie, whether you will conſider them as meer inſtruments or free agents enabled by God the mediate Cauſe to ſettle and convey this Principalitie upon whom and in what manner they pleaſe. Next we ſhall enquire, whether the people is the mediate, God the immediate Cauſe of this power; if you ſo conſider God and man, it followeth that the people worketh through God as a meer inſtrument or free agent receiving his authoritie from man. To averr either is hardly diſtinguiſhed from blaſphemie; therefore we will pitch upon the laſt conſideration of this Supremacie in the divine Law, and ſee whether God concurreth as a partiall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate cauſe with the people to produce and convey this power upon one or many, I ſhall admit unto you as your laſt refuge this mutuall and immediate concurrence, the people being but a partiall cauſe cannot in reaſon deveſt; as they did not alone inveſt this power, without the concurrence of God the ſociall cauſe: unleſſe you will ſay, the forfeiture and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of re-entrie to be onely reſerved to the people or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruing to them by Surviverſhip: either of theſe portents of opinions madneſſe it ſelfe will not own. Again, the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour and Creature cannot have the ſame numericall influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and if it could, the effect ſtill denominateth the worthier cauſe, therefore unleſſe the people be held the worthier cauſe they cannot properly or juſtly be called the authour or cauſe of this Supremacie. Hence is undeniably inferred, that the people are not nor cannot be ſtiled properly and juſtly the Cauſe mediate or immediate of Principalities. God is the Donor of Ariſtocracie and Monarchie, <hi>pag.</hi> 1. but few lines after of the ſame <hi>page</hi> you retract that opinion; diſſeize him of the title of Donor, holding God well repaid with the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of a Confirmer of Principalities:
<q>—Quo te mutantem Protea nodo.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:124359:12"/>
            <p>Firſt, a Donor to give a being, then rob him of that, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Confirmer to give a well being at moſt; the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Charter preſuppoſeth a Charter: God is a free Agent, ſuppoſe he ſuſpendeth or not at all confirmeth the popular conveyance, Is the conveyance void, or voidable? if void, then either the people giveth no being at all, or this being ſtill floweth, and not otherwiſe from them at that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant that God confirmeth it: and if it muſt alwayes flow from them at the ſame inſtant that God confirmeth it, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, eſcapeth (I believe) any mans reaſon to finde out. If void<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, then they give a being before God confirmeth it, and then popular election is ſuppoſable without divine concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; and if it be, the people prove efficients, and fall to be conſidered under one of the branches of efficients diſcuſſed before, and that they have not there the leaſt ſhadow to this pretended Soveraigntie is already and clearly evinced. Whether Nature entituleth them to this Royalneſſe reſteth next to be examined, <hi>Ignoratis terminis ignoratur ſcientia;</hi> we ſhall therefore explain what we mean by the Law of Nature: what dominion ariſeth by this Law of Nature, and in whom this dominion is naturally reſident, by the Law of Nature we underſtand <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſtatutes,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, right, and this is not in ſo large a ſenſe as the <hi>Roman</hi> Lawyers uſe it, for that which is common to man and beaſt, is improperly applied to beaſts, according to that of <hi>Heſiod.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>God gave mankinde a Law, which is</l>
                  <l>Deni'd to beaſt, wing'd fowle, and fiſh.</l>
                  <l>Theſe when ere their nature need</l>
                  <l>Do out upon another feed.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:124359:12"/>
            <p>But we reſtrain this to mankinde, and this reſtrained we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that which is properly the Law of Nature, which we conceived to be the dictate of right reaſon commanding or prohibiting an Act by the congruitie or incongruitie of the Act with rationall nature and conſequently injoyned or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by the Authour of Nature: Order and Subornati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is aſſigned by moſt Aſtronomers to celeſtiall Bodies, the Inhabitants of Heaven, I am aſſured by divine Authoritie, the Angels, Archangels, Principalities and Dominions; the Earth and the parts of it are created with ſubordinate De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendencie; the meaner Creatures of the Earth as Bees diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover in themſelves and actions Order and Subalternation in place and Authoritie; to deny this to Man, to whom all earthly Creatures were given; that Anarchie ſhould onely run in Mankinde, cannot be imagined to be intended by Nature or the Authour of it. The Word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo called for Order and Decencie, and ſhall this be denied to <hi>Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſmos</hi> the little world, Man? whoſe parts are guided by the Head, from thence proceed commands to all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. The contemplation of theſe Subordinations and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces invite us to conſider the World and the things therein with reſpect to the Head and Monarch of it Man; and in Man the worthier to whom Nature gave a reſpect and prio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; the Son as Son owing his being to his Father, owed him alſo Honour: hence <hi>Honour thy father, &amp;c.</hi> is re-written in the heart the characters that Nature firſt impreſt, being by the corruption of it blotted and defaced. Hereupon, <hi>Baſil</hi> wittily ſtileth a Parent, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a viſible Deitie, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs of the firſt age, as we have already urged, derived from their Father <hi>Adam</hi> Supremacie, and left to the firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne ſucceſſively in their Generations. The contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof induceth me to believe that had <hi>Adam</hi> ſtood in the ſtate of innocencie, one had been ſubject and ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to one another, but without tyrannie or oppreſſion on
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:124359:13"/>the Commanders part, or reluctancie on the Subject. When rapine and violence the iſſue of corrupted Nature broke forth, neceſſitie of ſafeguard forced men to draw into ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, the eaſier to protect themſelves; and from thence you ſay ſprung all Principalities: but whether the People choſe over themſelves Governours or Kings, or thoſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours and Kings made themſelves ſo at firſt over the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſeemeth to me not ſo evident, as the confidence of your Obſervations would have me believe: to lay aſide Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities that ſpeak of either, we will enquire after the Truth of this, eſpecially the Principalitie of the firſt Age by all the meanes reaſon can diſcover to us. When oppreſſion ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, probably it began in one, then more, and ſo in mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, and proportionably the number of the oppreſſed did encreaſe: the oppreſſour in caſe he prevailed was Lord over his Captives lives and eſtates, whoſe encreaſe and number encreaſed his Dominion, ſwelling by degrees to the extent of a conſiderable Monarchie: the oppreſſed whether one or more (it began with few) being not able to reſiſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence fled without queſtion for ſuccour to him whom they thought was able to defend them: and that he made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe King over them ſeemeth to me more probable, than that he was made by them; for it will be admitted on both ſides, the oppreſſed hath power to ſubject himſelfe, and the protectour power to command it; for the oppreſſed ſheltreth himſelfe probably under a ſtronger patronage than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: without queſtion then the Patron would erect and enlarge his Dominion with more ſpeed and will, than the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed would undergo perpetuall ſlaverie, the one being diſſonant to Nature, the other congruous to humane ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: hence we gather by our conſideration of the probable actions of the firſt oppreſſours, and oppreſſed, Principalitie forced by oppreſſion cannot claime in any likelihood its ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall from the People: and Dominion thus gained whileſt it
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:124359:13"/>is not accompanied with tyrannie cannot be called unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, or to croſſe the dictates of reaſon, reaſon embraceth that which it forſeth beſt to prevent violence and ſettle qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe; and that which Nature delighteth moſt in, can no way be held unnaturall, witneſſe the workes of it, all woven in ſubjection and dependencie, only oppreſſion too frequent a companion of Soveraigntie in corrupted Nature is that which is contrariant to Nature, and the chiefe cauſe of all contracts between King and people. Laſtly, let us ſee what footing your popular Supremacie hath in the Law of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which is defined to be a humane voluntary Law and obligative among all or moſt Nations, that Law Supremacie was acknowledged by all or moſt Nations to be the end and efficient of all powers is neither affirmed nor proved by you. Their conſtant practice as we have touched already diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing your opinion, and if you joyne this iſſue with me, you will never be able to give in evidence any convincing teſtimonie, but we ſhall expect your <hi>palinodia,</hi> with <hi>Tu vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisti me &amp; ego errorem,</hi> orthodoxally concurring with our opinion, that power is not originally inherent in the people <hi>de facto,</hi> or by any Law. The reſult of our diſcourſe is that Monarchies and all other Govenments owe their originall to God, who is the Donor efficient and ultimate end of them, the people are by him made the inſtrument to convey this, but not all people, nor at all times. The King and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are the ſubordinate end of the Government they live in. Kings contracts with their Subjects in a Government, gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Conqueſt is more the Princes bounty, than a diſcharge of his dutie; and if otherwiſe, Princes ſo ſettled cannot be removed or forcibly reſiſted by the people without trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Rebellion againſt God and his Deputie. The reſidue of your diſcourſe is either matter of fact, admonitions, or ſarcaſmes. for the matter of fact, as I do not diſallow the truth of any of them, ſo I do not much credit a ſingle teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:124359:14"/>eſpecially of him whoſe eyes are infected with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Jandize, ſees the Kings actions all of one colour. Sarcaſme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are diſallowed by the holy Text againſt the ſacred perſon or a King, <hi>Ne maledices principi in populo tuo, Deuter.</hi> 22.28. or foment Rebellion with malitious paradoxes againſt Gods Annointed; and if by a <hi>Pythagorean</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Therſites</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth in your Antipathie to Regall Government, moſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> hearts will with me returne unto you the checke <hi>Therſites</hi> had;
<q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
